Daniel: Selamat datang semuanya, ini adalah "Bit dari DPL"
dengan Pemimpin Proyek Debian, Stefano Zacchiroli
jadi, mari kita bertepuk tangan, Saya pikir ia tidak perlu diperkenalkan
Stefano: Terima kasih
[tepuk-tangan]
Jadi, saya yakin Anda di sini karena ini akan jadi yang terakhir
Saya akan usik Anda dengan pembicaraan "Bit dari DPL",
setidaknya saat DebConf, jadi terima kasih sudah hadir.
Pada sesi ini, Saya akan membaginya menjadi dua bagian:
bagian pertama merupakan semacam... kumpulan mantra
yang telah menjadi cara bagaimana Saya mendefinisikan Debian hari ini.
Saya telah mempresentasikan ke beragam orang sebelumnya
Saya lihat terdapat cukup orang di dalam ruangan
hal ini takkan jadi masalah karena jadi pertama kali mereka mendengarnya,
jadi Saya harap Anda akan mengizinkan saya untuk mengulasnya.
Dan selanjutnya, setelah mendefinisikan mantra Debian,
Saya akan mempresentasikan tantangan yang saya pikir kita hadapi dalam Debian
dan yang perlu kita pikirkan
untuk menjamin kita memiliki hidup yang sehat dan panjang umur ke depannya.
Tapi sebelumnya, saya mencoba membuat poin yang membuat kita menorehkan sejarah.
Jadi, beginilah Debian dimulai pada tahun 1993,
kutipan pertama.
1993 sudah hampir 20 tahun yang lalu.
Saat itu hanya ada sangat sedikit distribusi GNU/Linux,
dan mereka... memiliki banyak masalah,
dan kualitasnya tidak apik
dan orang-orang mulai berpikir tentang
"bagaimana kita membuat GNU/Linux kompetitif dengan sistem operasi komersial?"
dan Ian Murdock datang dengan ide hebat Debian
dan saat inilah semuanya dimulai.
Lantas kami menorehkan sejarah paling tidak dengan dua cara:
satu adalah dengan komunitas dan jalan sosial:
dalam wawancara beberapa tahun lalu,
Ian menyatakan bahwa Debian merupakan proyek komunitas terencana pertama yang terbentuk;
sebelumnya terdapat distro,
sebelumnya terdapat proyek Free Software,
tapi Debian merupakan desain dengan komunitas di dalam pikiran
dan dengan ide yang jika Anda ingin sesuatu dapat sebesar ukuran Debian hari ini
kami membutuhkan komunitas di belakangnya.
Jadi, saya pikir kami telah menorehkan sejarah
menunjukkan bagaimana sebuah proyek sebesar Debian
hanya dapat dibuat dengan partisipasi aktif komunitas.
Namun selanjutnya, kami juga menorehkan sejarah secara teknis:
dua-puluh tahun telah lewat sejak tahun 1993
dan jika kita lihat Debian sekarang
kami memiliki hingga empat ratus ribu paket biner,
tepatnya dalam Debian;
kami telah membuat 12 rilis
dan - siapa tahu? - mungkin kami akan membuat yang ke-13 sebelum akhir tahun ini;
kami memiliki proyek dengan jumlah anggota hampir seribu;
dan hampir 200 orang Debian Maintainers
yang tertarik untuk menjaga beberapa bagian Debian;
dan ribuan kontributor mengerjakan hal-hal lainnya
yang berguna untuk proyek.
Kami memiliki jumlah port terbanyak
diantara - sebut saja - distribusi biner "major" di luar sana.
Kami memiliki non-Linux ports:
kami telah merilis versi Debian yang bekerja dengan kernel selain Linux.
Kami belum merilis versi Debian yang bekerja dengan kernel seperti Hurd
tapi untuk mereka yang suka dengan Hurd dan ingin mencobanya
Debian masih menjadi pilihan terbaik untuk melakukannya.
Hebat! Inilah kita, membuat ini semua!
Bravo! Untuk semuanya! Kita membuatnya!
Namun, satu hal menorehkan sejarah
But then, one thing is making history
dalam beragam cara, baik secara teknis mapun sosial
dan hal yang sangat berbeda pun masih tetap relevan.
Jadi, dalam tiga tahun belakang sebagai DPL
So, in these past three years as DPL
Saya menghadapi permasalahan yang orang-orang mulai pertanyakan
- itu seperti beberapa tahun yang lalu -
"Apakah kita masih membutuhkan Debian?"
"Ok, Anda telah menorehkan sejarah, membuat banyak hal
Anda membuat turunan, Anda membuat banyak hal tapi ...
... Apakah kami masih membutuhkan Debian hari ini?"
Saya menanyakan diri saya sendiri untuk menjawab pertanyaan ini
dan jalan untuk menjawab pertanyaan adalah dengan bertanya ke diri sendiri
apa yang berbeda dari apa yang kita lakukan dan distro lain lakukan.
Terdapat hingga tiga ratus, empat ratus distro Free Software di seluruh dunia:
apa yang membuat Debian spesial?
Dan saya mulai berpikir beberapa jawaban dari pertanyaan tersebut
dan saya telah menemukan lima perlakuan spesifik yang membuat - saya pikir - Proyek Debian unik.
Saya pikir sangat berguna untuk mengingatnya
dan untuk mengingatkan mengapa kita berkontribusi ke Debian dan buka ke proyek serupa lainnya.
Alasan pertama,
dan merupakan mantra yang membuat Debian spesial,
adalah kebebasan.
Hal ini seperti jelas namun sebenarnya terdapat beragam kebebasan.
Alasan pertama mengapa Debian spesial dalam hal kebebasan
adalah kita telah setuju dengan publik (masyarakat) dan dengan publik Free Software
bahwa Debian akan selalu bebas.
Kita telah mempromosikan budaya Free Software, kita tak hanya memberikan Free Software ke masyarakat,
kita telah mempromosikan budaya Free Software sejak 1993,
dan kita memiliki produk yang bebas dari bawah hingga atas
terdapat banyak sekali "makanan anjing" dari yang kita lakukan.
Jadi bebas dalam perangkat lunak, kita berikan kepada masyarakat
dan bebas bagaimana kita membuatnya.
Setiap bit dari infrastruktur Debian adalah bebas
dan tak seorang pun mau menerima jika kita membuat Debian menggunakan seperti
and nobody would accept if we start making Debian using like
hal-hal tidak-bebas dalam infrastruktur kita.
Hal ini merupakan tindakan tak umum.
Dan kita juga memiliki angan-angan bebas
dalam proses yang kita gunakan.
Mereka yang telah di Debian sejak lama
telah mendengar motto "Tidak ada Sekongkol!"
sebagai lelucon, beberapa kali.
Dan kita menggunakan dengan mengatakan, dalam berpikir tidak ada sekongkol
namun poin dari jika kita membuat lelucon ini
bahwa itu berarti kita tidak dapat menerima ide bahwa terdapat seseorang
membawa Debian dengan motif tersembunyi,
membawa Debian tidak secara terbuka.
Jadi kami tidak lagi bebas di dalam infrastruktur,
tidak hanya dalam perangkat lunak yang kami buat,
namun juga dalam tindakan yang kami lakukan.
Kami coba se-transparan mungkin yang kami bisa.
Dan hal inilah yang menarik bagi saya
bahwa terdapat semacam kesadaran komunitas
bahwa hal semacam ini yang kami miliki untuk kebebasan.
Komunitas kita mempercayai kita untuk tidak berkhianat pada prinsip kebebasan
dan mereka berpikir bahwa ini merupakan kontribusi sangat tinggi untuk Free Software
jadi kami telah menetapkan target yang sangat tinggi
untuk menentukan kapan sesuatu itu bebas atau tidak.
Saat masyarakat membutuhkan keputusan apakah suatu perangkat lunak itu bebas atau dengan lisensi
yang perlu dipertimbangkan Fress Software atau tidak
mereka dasarnya mengacu pada tiga entitas:
mereka mengacu ke Free Software Foundation,
mereka mengacu ke OSI,
they go to the OSI,
mereka pergi ke Debian
dan mereka melihat apakan lisensi dipertimbangkan bebas
oleh tiga entitas tersebut. Dan kita salah satunya.
Jadi poin pertama, yang saya pikir menentukan apa yang kita lakukan dalam Debian, adalah kebebasan.
Poin kedua adalah semacam perfeksionis
yang seringkali menyerang balik kita
yang membuat...
yang hadir akibat dari pilihan kita
namun kami memiliki semacam budaya keunggulan teknikal.
Kita memiliki Kebijakan, di mana telah kita kodifikasi kebutuhan kualitas untuk paket;
kita memiliki jumlah besar sekali dari testing: kita punya Lintian, kita punya Piuparts;
kita memiliki pengujian otomatis untuk melihat apakah paket mematuhi Kebijakan;
kita memiliki maintainer yang merupakan pakar perangkat lunak.
Kita mencoba mendorong orang untuk me-maintain perangkat lunak di Debian jika mereka mengerti soal pemaketan
kita mencoba mendorong orang untuk me-maintain perangkat lunak yang mereka gunakan
dan perangkat lunak yang mereka merupakan pakar dengannya
dan ini merupakan suatu hal yang besar dalam hal dukungan pengguna.
Jadi saat pengguna datang kepada kami
datang maintainer yang dihormati dari beberapa perangkat lunak dalam Debian,
umumnya ia menemukan sesorang yang mengetahui bagian spesifik dari perangkat lunak.
Ini, untuk kami, adalah kualitas.
Kita memiliki paket yang mereka semua memiliki persyaratan kualitas yang sama
dan tidak terdapat paket... tidak ada perbedaan dalam arsip Debian yang mengatakan
"kami coba untuk persyaratan kualitas ini untuk satu bagian dari arsip
dan bagian lainnya untuk bagian lain dari arisp".
Dan kami juga mengatakan "Kami rilis saat siap"
ini merupakan cara kami mengatakan
kami tidak dapat menjanjikan hingga tanggal tertentu
karena kami taku akan isu temuan, isu kualitas, sebelum waktu rilis
dan kami takut berkompromi dengan kualitas rilis untuk tanggal tertentu.
Jadi kami katakan "kami rilis saat sudah siap"
hal ini merupakan soal kualitas.
Poin ketiga, dan sesuatu yang penting untuk yang akan saya katakan selanjutnya,
adalah kemerdekaan.
Jika Anda lihat sekitar ekosistem distro di luar sana
Anda tidak akan menemukan banyak distro di mana
Anda tidak dapat menunjuk perusahaan yang mendukung suatu distro.
Diantara distro besar, kami hanya satu diantaranya
yang berjalan seluruhnya berdasarkan basis relawan
tidak ada korporat atau semacam struktur hirarkis
di mana keputusan diambil dari atas ke bawah.
Kita tidak memiliki satu perusahaan yang menjaga
dan pada dasarnya kami hidup dengan donasi,
dalam bentuk waktu, relawan mengkontribusikan waktunya untuk Debian
dan donasi dalam bentuk uang
Hal ini sangat luar biasa
dalam ekosistem hari ini, khususnya dalam distro Free Software.
Dan sekali kita memiliki fenomena kewaspadaan komunitas:
And once more we have a phenomenon of community awareness:
komunitas kita akan mempercaya, berdasarkan kemerdekaan kita,
keputusan dalam Debian takkan diambil berdasarkan alasan keuntungan
atau alasan lainnya yang bertentangan dengan nilai dasar kita.
Jadi, kemerdekaan adalah nilai lain yang sangat penting, bagi saya, hal ini yang memotivasi saya berkontribusi ke Debian.
Dan selanjutnya, kita punya pengambilan keputusan.
Pengambilan keputusan adalah sesuatu yang sangat diatur dalam Undang-undang kita.
Aturan dasarnya, yang saya mulai sebut sebagai do-ocracy
- sebenarnya istilah ini saya ambil dari orang lain tapi saya tidak ingat dari siapa saya ambil,
namun sepertinya cukup cocok -
dasarnya mengatakan jika seseorang bertanggung jawab untuk melakukan suatu pekerjaan dalam Debian,
selama mereka melakukan pekerjaannya, hmm, mereka yang memutuskan bagaimana melakukannya.
Tidak seorang pun dapat pergi ke sana dan berkata: "Anda perlu melakukannya dengan cara ini",
kecuali
mereka telah siap berkomitmen dan melakukan pekerjaan ini sendiri.
Dan ini merupakan aturan default.
Semua keputusan dalam Debian, secara default,
All decisions in Debian, by default, diambil dengan cara ini
lalu kita juga punya demokrasi:
Kita telah melihat beberapa potensi perbaikan dalam hal kita mengambil keputusan.
Jadi kita diperbolehkan untuk mengambil keputusan bersama,
dengan cara demokratis, dengan pemungutan suara.
Kami cukup bijak untuk hanya mengatakan, dan secara umum, untuk alasan politis
dan untuk alasan filosofis
Kami mencoba untuk tidak melakukannya karena alasan teknis
namun kami dapat melakukannya bahkan untuk alasan teknis.
Jadi kami mencoba melakukannya seperti ini
sebagai semacam cara untuk membuat cara default bagaimana pengambilan keputusan bekerja.
Dan apa arti ini semua?
Hal ini berarti sangat mudah untuk memberi efek ke Debian
jika Anda mengetahui bagaimana melakukan sesuatu dalam Debian dan tak seorang pun melakukannya,
Anda dapat memilihnya
dan jika Anda mulai melakukannya, Anda yang akan memutuskan bagaimana melakukannya.
Jadi, hal inilah mudahnya memberi efek ke Debian terima kasih pada cara kita mengambil keputusan
namun hal ini berarti juga reputasi dalam proyek mengikuti kerja
jika Anda memiliki reputasi yang baik dalam proyek umumnya disebabkan Anda telah melakukan banyak hal
dan sangat banyak pekerjaan berkualitas tinggi.
Dan akhir kata, sekali lagi, itu berarti tidak keputusan yang dikenakan
tidak seperti orang yang memiliki infrastruktur
atau mereka yang mempekerjakan orang
dapat memutuskan bagaimana keputusan dibuat
keputusan dibuat seperti ini.
Dan poin terakhir,
And last point,
kita telah mengakhiri menjadi semacam root
dari ekosistem besar derivatif.
Saya percaya Anda semua tahu apa itu yang dimaksud derivatif:
Anda mengambil distro yang sudah ada,
Anda mulai mengkompilasi paket-paket,
tambahkan paket Anda sendiri, Anda mengganti beberapa hal
lalu Anda dapatkan sebuah distro yang benar-benar baru.
Hal ini yang mulai terjadi akhir-akhir ini
- mulai terjadi secara masif -
dalam - katakan saja - sepuluh tahun
dan yang benar-benar mengubah bagaimana produk distro dibuat.
Derivatif dapat fokus pada kustomisasi
dan mengambil untung dari semua pekerjaan yang dilakukan dari distro induknya
dan Debian berakhir sebagai root pada sesuatu seperti
140 distro aktif
menurut distrowatch.
Hal ini berarti pekerjaan yang kita lakukan dalam Debian
tidak hanya relevan untuk - katakan saja - pengguna "langsung" kita sendiri,
hal ini berguna untuk pengguna dari distro semacam ini
yang termasuk distro paling populer di luar sana.
Orang di luar sana, biarpun mereka tidak tahu, bergantung pada banyak pekerjaan dalam Debian
dan saya pikir hal ini hebat.
Ringkasnya, poin saya di sini adlaah Debian memiliki peran yang sangat penting untuk dimainkan
secara umum dalam ekosistem Free Software
dan jika kita gagal dalam melakukan apa yang harus kita lakukan
tidak hanya pengguna Debian langsung yang akan gagal.
Saya pikir secara umum Free Software akan menderita dari kegagalan Debian menyampaikan apa yang kita pikirkan.
Jadi pertanyaanya adalah:
So the question is:
apakah kita peduli dengan apa yang harus kita lakukan dalam Free Software secara umum?
Dan saya telah melihat beberapa tantangan yang ingin saya diskusikan dengan Anda.
Tantangan pertama adalah untuk tetap sehat
dan untuk tetap sehat
sebuah proyek Free Software, untuk relawan proyek Free Software, dasarnya berarti
dapat merekrut orang
untuk menemukan relawan baru untuk bergabung ke proyek
dan jika Anda telah mendengar saya berbicara di DebConfi selama dua tahun
atau secara umum ke publik pengembang Debian
kita telah mendiskusikan kurangnya sumber daya manusia
sebagai masalah utama dalam proyek:
kita tidak dapat melakukan sesuatu karena kurang sumber daya manusia.
Faktanya saya telah menelusuri data
and our recruitment, if we can call it this way, is going very well.
Over the past two years
we have had thirty new DDs
more every single year
this is net in the sense that this is an actual increase on the number of DD
I have already discounted the number of DDs that dropped off the project
because of some sort of natural turnover.
Thirty DDs per year is quite a lot.
And if we look at maintainers, Debian Maintainers,
we have something like fifty new Debian Maintainers per year
this is gross because I didn't find the actual net data
but it still give an idea that we do, we are able to recruit people
both to work on Debian in general
- whatever the task -
and to work on specific packages in the archive.
I think we should really stop using the lack of manpower as an excuse
we are a volunteer project: we will always lack manpower to do something
but our ability to recruit new people is doing well
is doing very well.
What we really need to do is to actually better use the manpower that we do have
and, in particular, I'm worried about
the barriers for contribution that exist within the Debian Project.
One thing we discuss often is
we don't need people to maintain yet another package in the Debian archive
what we need is people working on some of the core teams
the infrastructure teams or maintaining the very important packages in the archive.
But the key to make that work
is to make it easier for people to contribute to those teams.
We have a lot of services in Debian which are very difficult to contribute to
we have services which are online
which have no mentions of where is the code behind those services
of where to report bugs for those services.
These are all small attentions we could use
to make it easier to contribute within the Debian Project
and if someone starts working on some leaf package in the archive
and if he find easier to contribute to some more important stuff
they will do that.
In fact that's how I think most of us that got involved in the Debian Project
ended up doing more and more important stuff
starting from the easy part and climbing up at bit
doing the more complex stuff.
So, if you are working on something within the Debian Project
in addition to think at the work you're doing
please think at "how can I make it easier
for others to contribute to this?"
"have I documented how to contribute to this?"
"have I put a link of where is the source code of this thing I maintain in Debian?"
"have I mentioned who should they contact for a project?"
all this kind of questions.
This is what will help in better using the manpower we have in Debian.
And another one, and someone will probably kill me for this,
is diversity in various senses.
I think we've realized
that to do an operating system like Debian
we need a lot of skills:
packaging is not enough,
packaging is one piece in the puzzle
but we need a lot of other stuff.
We need translations,
we need people doing artwork,
we need system administrators,
we need porters,
and all this kind of skills are quite different,
we need software developers,
and good packagers are not necessarily good software developers and vice versa.
We need a whole lot of different skills
and we do should not think that packagers are good at doing all of it
it is not the case: the skills needed are very different.
This is one reason why I think diversity is good
for a project like Debian
but I think it's good also for the discussion culture in Debian:
if you know that in a discussion place
you will find people that have very different backgrounds from yours,
very different point of view than yours,
then you need to be more cautious about how you write things
you need to make less assumptions when you write things
so having a more diverse project
actually helps also in having a better discussion culture.
This is the second reason why I think diversity is good for Debian.
We've done a lot in the past few years
we've sort of fixed the membership process
making it clear that we do welcome people with a wide range of skills joining Debian
and we have also, more recently, fixed the nm.debian.org website
to make it clear... to avoid implicit assumptions
that there are only packagers that we welcome.
This is great, we've done that.
But as Christian mentioned in the previous talk, stealing my argument
we are not doing very well
at attracting people who do stuff other than packaging:
in two years we've attracted only five people
in this so called "non-uploading" DD category,
only five people decided to join Debian as a project members
and said
"you know, I don't really care about packaging
I want to do something else in the Debian Project
and I commit to do that on a longer basis
but I do understand the values of the Debian Project and I'm ready to uphold them".
Only five is a bit ... it's quite a few
sorry, it's not too much.
We really need to understand how to invite
people with different backgrounds than packaging
to join the Debian Project.
I think that diversity statement we sent out
is a step in the right direction, but we need to do more:
I don't know what exactly, but we really need to do more to attract those
kind of people.
Some other challenges are related to the release process.
I'm still amazed that people on the net
still complain that Debian has unpredictable release cycles:
the other day I replied on Linux Weekly News to someone who was complaining
that Sarge has been very much delayed as release.
Yes, that's true:
Sarge has been a delayed release,
like three years or something
but it is something which happened seven years ago.
Even in the time frame of Debian, that's a lot,
that's one third of our time in existence.
Since then we have learned:
the release cycle of Etch
took 22 months,
same for the release cycle of Lenny.
The release cycle of Squeeze took 24 months.
All of these look pretty much predictable to me.
I think we are doing well on that front
and starting with Wheezy,
for the first time in our history,
we've done time based freezes.
You probably know that I'm a huge fan of that
not all of us agree with that
but I think that is a huge step forward
because it helps developers in planning ahead changes.
Yes, there are people that will upload the last minute no matter what,
I understand that,
but for all the people who want to plan ahead
that's a huge help.
And it also helps our upstreams:
there are upstreams out there
who very much care about the version of their packages that will end up
in a stable Debian release.
There are people out there that if they know we freeze on a specific date
they will commit to give long term support for that software.
So knowing a freeze date in advance is a huge help for them.
I think we should keep this in mind,
keep in mind what was not working with the previous model,
like people getting upset of abort freeze
without knowing in advance when they were going happen.
And I think we should try to not forget this
aim in the future at reliably freezing every x months.
24? Maybe.
More than that?
Fewer than that? I don't know.
But I think we should try to keep this in mind and maintain that in the
future.
And in case you didn't notice:
Wheezy is frozen!
And we did this with a time based freeze.
I think it worked well
but there is still a lot of work to do
and in particular
we have frozen with something like
135 more RC-bugs with respect to the previous stable release.
There is a lot of work to do for all of us.
In this work which is ahead of us
I think we should really aim to have a short freeze period
that's something we should aim to.
It will happen or it will not happen it depends on us,
but I think it should be a goal.
It should be a goal because it will show us that
time based freeze is a sustainable model
even if it means freezing with a bit more bugs than before
it will reduce the period of time
in which we are bit frustrated
in which we cannot do far reaching changes.
The shorter we can keep this period
it will be better for people who really want to make some more profund
changes.
Asheesh do you have a question?
Sorry?
Asheesh: How short is good?
Stefano: So the question is how short is good.
Well, I don't know
I think it should be a goal
I don't think we can say...
Well, I mean, staying within the limits of the past trend
like six months
I think that's would be good.
Better would be shorter than that.
But this is not really a question for me, this is more for the release team
but I think we should have in mind
that we should do all we can
to keep that as short as possible.
And also there are distributions out there
that rely on testing
we do have in mind a single product, which is Debian stable
which is a great product
but, like it or not,
people out there are using Debian testing as a product
they're using it on their desktop machines,
on their development machines
because it's kind of
the thing that invented rolling distributions out there.
And it's a great suite.
Keeping it short
keeping the release - ehm, sorry - the freeze period short,
will also help other people that rely on something like Debian testing.
How do we do that?
I don't think it's really normal to have that many release critical bugs
at the freeze point
it means that there are maintainers... it means two things
that there are very hard bugs to fix, which is normal,
but it also means that there are some maintainers
that they kind of neglected their work
that they didn't manage to complete to clean up
their packages of release critical bugs before the freeze.
But it happens
we are here, it has happened in the past, it will happen again in the
future.
So the only way I think we have to release at this point
is to, once again, keep in mind that releasing
is not something that the release team does alone
they cannot release Wheezy alone.
I've been bothering you with this idea since ever
since way before I became the DPL
but I think the only solution we have for this
is doing NMUs,
accepting NMUs,
welcoming NMUs,
loving NMUs
every single day, please, have a look
at the list of release critical bugs reports.
I look at this graph, essentially, every morning
and also after coffee, to see how we are going
really, please do the same!
Then, please, every day
look up if there is a release critical bug you can fix
even, and especially, if it is not in your package.
There are people, like Gregor - who is somewhere here in the room -
that every single day - thanks Gregor -
every single day try to do that
and publish the initiative to make other do the same
he is not the only one, a lot of other people are doing that
but also publishing it is very good.
And, really, NMUs that fix RC-bugs
are free for all
do them properly, try to make it clear that you're trying to help
the maintainer of the involved package
but please: that's the only way
we're going to release Wheezy
really.
And if you want another way of looking at this,
it's for the software engineering fan,
is collective code ownership.
So, collective code ownership is a notion that
well, this term comes from extreme programming
and essentially says that all programmers
have access to all of the code of a project
so that no single person can be a bottle neck
on a specific part of the project.
This is considered good in agile development,
this is considered a best practice to follow
in open source project management,
but in some way it is not always considered good in Debian.
Which is kind of weird.
In the past we didn't have the notion of maintainer
then, Bdale will correct me if I'm wrong, in 1995
has been introduced.
Is it right? Something like that? Ok thanks.
And with that we sort of added some barriers.
There are useful stuff behind the notion of maintainer
like pride in what you do, being recognized for the work you do
which is great.
But we should also keep in mind that there are barriers
with the notion of maintainer
that make it harder
for others to contribute to your package.
So the best approximation we have
to collective code ownership in Debian
is essentially being more liberal with NMUs
and team maintenance,
but we don't have teams which are as large as the Debian Project.
So liberal NMUs is really our best approximation
for collective code ownership in Debian.
And then, moving to the past two,
which probably will be a bit more controversial.
Low company involvement, I think is becoming a problem in Debian.
If you look at other similar project to Debian
with the same kind of history and with the same size,
you'll see that Debian has less paid work opportunity around
and you'll see that we have few companies which are contributing
directly.
Think at the Linux kernel:
everyone who can show that can get code in the Linux kernel
will find a job in five minutes.
We do have companies that will be happy to hire Debian Developers
but not as much as you have around a project like the Linux kernel.
So, for me, volunteering is great
I wouldn't work on Debian on paid time, I would not do that.
I work on Free Software for volunteering reasons
it matches my view of society where
each of us has a work
and some extra time, after work,
in which he does something to contribute to society
so this is not really for me.
But I think it could be a problem for Debian in general.
Why?
We do compete
with companies and their full staff - sorry - and their full time
employees.
So, our competitors are commercial distributions
with huge means in terms of employees who are working on the distro.
That's fine, we don't do Free Software only to make money
but we need to watch out for our morale.
So, when we start thinking stuff like
"Debian is not innovating anymore"
"It is other distributions innovating"
well, we need to keep in mind that
the ratio of forces in the field may not be very well balanced.
This is the first problem that I think having low company contributing to
Debian.
Second reason is that
there are useful tasks out there
that volunteers won't bother doing.
I've been asked many many times:
"why don't you go to hardware vendors and convince them
to pre-install Debian on their machines?"
Well, try to find a volunteer that is happy to spend his time
in, you know, lobbying hardware producers to install Debian on it.
That's an example.
Other examples are all sort of certification lobbying:
something that very often public administrations ask me
is why Debian is not certified for
random very high quality corporate database system.
Why Debian is not certified for that unnamed system?
Well, because you need lobbying to do that,
you need people going to the
software vendors and convince them to say "Yes, you can run this on
Debian".
Otherwise, there are people out there that won't run Debian.
And all sort of other stuff,
like creating a sort of networks that makes
specific adopters convinced them they will be fine adopting Debian.
And the last reason why I think we need a bit more of companies involved in Debian
is a sort of disturbing thought.
What if only one company or a few companies, for what it's worth
end up hiring the whole lot of DDs?
The independence I've been babbling around before will be gone.
This is not paranoia.
This is a kind of problem that has been discussed,
for instance, in the Linux kernel community for a long time.
They know that they have some sort of independence because they have
many different companies
with interest in the Linux kernel
which sort of balance each other.
So if we don't have more companies interested in Debian
we'll risk ending up in that situation.
Some sort of very early work in progress
which I've tried to kick start
is a sort of user group, debian-companies,
of companies who have some strategic interest in Debian
and want to try to work on fixing this problem.
They may be other solutions,
I don't know, I wanted to present this as problem
as I think that in the long run we'll need to think about it.
And the last thing is the DPL.
Which happens to be me at the moment.
What does the DPL do for you?
According to my family possibly too much
but that's a separate problem.
He does fancy stuff:
he goes to conferences, he's all around the world, he's invited to talk about Debian
and he has a wikipedia page and all this kind of fancy stuff.
But he also has to do
all sort of needed but pretty boring, for the average geek, stuff.
He has to take care of money:
approving reimbursements,
buying hardware,
DebConf, donations
trying to avoid bankruptcy,
which is a nice thing to do.
And he needs to take care of lawyers.
I've never been working with lawyers
as much as in the last three years.
He takes care of what we do with patents:
can we have it in the archive or not,
what we do with trademarks,
what we do with copyright, for instance,
can we relicense the Debian logo
without undermining some other asset we have?
And legal responsibility:
and what if a Debian Developer get a lawsuit?
All this sort of stuff,
which is useful,
because if we now have a bit more
- how to say? - enhanced multimedia experience in Debian
is also because we take the time
to discuss this stuff down with lawyers that are experts in Free
Software.
And he does mediations,
and he does reports.
How many reports from me have you got in the past three years?
Yeah, too many!
This is all sort of boring stuff
which I think is useful for the project.
But then, as it is today, the DPL is a problem.
I am a problem, but it's not me, it's the role of DPL who has a problem
in Debian.
It just does not scale.
We basically rely on some sort of luck
that we will find
candidates that will have enough time to do all of this
and it's quite a bit of time.
I don't know if it's wise to only rely on luck
to finding those people
over the years forever.
Second problem: transparency is very hard.
I've tried to... I've worked quite a bit on that:
I think I spend like half of my time
as DPL
in trying to tell you what is going on
and only the other half on working on stuff.
I've been happy to do that, but is very hard.
And as long as I'm talking to myself
or replying to inquiries that come to the Leader's mailbox
there are some sort of intrinsic limits:
if you are in a team with more people
you need to discuss things
and if you force yourself to discuss things publicly
you don't have these intrinsic limits.
And the third problem is that there is very little institutional memory.
We keep on, essentially, rediscover the job
at each DPL change.
Yes, I can write a DPL Howto
with the help of all past DPLs.
We can do that, but things change
and essentially the key of the problem is that
being the DPL is unlike any other task in the project:
it's difficult to know who will be a good DPL before
because he or she has never done that before
and there is essentially only trial and error.
There is very little institutional memory of how to do things.
How can we fix this?
I've been thinking a lot about this,
is one of the reason why I decided to run again for a third term,
essentially I think the problem is that
the role of the DPL is a relic of the "benevolent dictator" era in the
Free Software.
It made a sense in the past,
today projects of the size of Debian are not run in this way
not even for only the management part.
We do not do the technical part with a benevolent dictator, which is very
good,
but we do that for all the kind of management part.
I think the only solution possible here
is have some sort of board of directors
as other projects have
which essentially helps the DPL.
The role of the DPL should not disappear.
I think we should try to keep this as informal as possible
but if we have a group of people that we can call the Debian Board of Directors
that can have some sort of turnover
to guarantee that there is some institutional memory
so they should not be tied to the normal DPL period,
otherwise you'd have the problem of institutional memory again,
with periodic meetings for transparency
and if we do have this
you can have the people on this kind of board
that help out and show if themselves they will be able to do
good DPLs or not.
I think this is the only way
to make the role of the DPL scalable
without changing the nature of what the institution is.
And as an interim solution
I'm trying to collect a group of DPL helpers
you've seen the call for help, thanks to all the people who replied.
So what I'm trying to do is to
try to see if this kind of things could work.
And yet, the DPL will remain.
So, given I'm here basically because someone
a few years ago started joking about me becoming DPL,
well, this is a good occasion for all of you
to start think at the next one
and maybe start joking with him
whether he or she will be happy to candidate the next year.
So, thanks a lot
it's a pleasure to be here
and if you have questions or thoughts I'm available.
Thanks
[applause]